A Guide to the Papers of Mary Johnston
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Mary Johnston
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3588
This collection consists of ca. 4000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Papers of Mary Johnston were deposited by Elizabeth Johnston November 1, 1960 and became the property of the University of Virginia when she died.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mary Johnston was born November 21, 1870 in Buchanan, Virginia to Elizabeth Alexander Johnston from Moorefield, West Virginia and John W. Johnston, lawyer and railway executive, of Botetourt County, Virginia. Mary Johnston, the oldest of six children, was followed by Eloise Johnston, Anne Johnston, John Johnston, Walter Johnston, and Elizabeth Johnston; the first and last two siblings lived most of their adult lives with Mary Johnston until her death, and they are mentioned frequently in these papers.
The family moved to Birmingham, Alabama in 1886 and, except for a brief period spent in New York City around 1893 remained in Birmingham until 1902 when they moved to Richmond, Virginia. Elizabeth Alexander Johnston died in 1889 soon after the birth of her last child. John W. Johnston, a Confederate soldier and cousin to General Joseph E. Johnston, died in 1905, and soon thereafter Mary Johnston became critically ill, hovering close to death for nearly a year. Although she recovered and lived until 1936, she was plagued with horrible headaches and ill health most of her life. In 1912 Mary Johnston and Eloise Johnston bought land and built a home, "Three Hills," in Warm Springs, Virginia; this remained the Johnston family home until Elizabeth Johnston's death in the 1960's.
Mary Johnston was not formally educated but apparently did a great deal of undirected reading in her youth, particularly of literature, history, philosophy, and science. She loved nature and, as a young adult, travelled frequently in Europe. She began writing in 1893, and her novel, Prisoner of Hope, which appeared in 1898, was her first publication. Houghton, Mifflin and Co. published her novels until she changed to Harpers in 1918; in 1922 she moved to Little-Brown and Co. Her literary agent was Carl Brandt. Mary Johnston published twenty-three novels--the earlier ones such as To Have and To Hold, Audrey, Sir Mortimer, Lewis Rand, and The Long Roll were the most popular--one play, The Goddess of Reason; one historical work, The Pioneers of the Old South; and numerous short stories.
In addition to her literary and feminist activities, Mary Johnston was a self-declared pacifist in World War I and worked for peace through various organizations. She also had a great interest in socialism, although she never joined the Socialist Party. In later years she studied theosophy with much enthusiasm.
Scope and Content
The Papers of Mary Johnston consists of ca. 4000 items, including correspondence (both personal and professional), literary manuscripts, dramatic adaptations, diaries, accounts and cashbooks, photographs, speeches and news clippings.
Arrangement
The correspondence with family, friends, agents, and publishers has been arranged alphabetically by the correspondents; this correspondence comprises the first seven boxes. The miscellaneous family, suffrage and other correspondence is in chronological order and occupies boxes 8-10. Boxes 11-19 contain the manuscripts of stories, novels, and dramatic adaptations and have been arranged alphabetically by title. The diaries and copies of diaries are arranged chronologically in boxes 20 and 21. In boxes 21-22 are are rough drafts of the biography compiled by her sister from Mary Johnston's diaries and unfinished autobiography. Box 23 contains genealogical material, and boxes 24-25 contain accounts and cashbooks. In box 26 are contracts and other legal papers, as well as photographs. Box 27 holds manuscripts of speeches on suffrage, labor, books and the Civil War, and box 28 contains miscellaneous personal articles. The remainder of box 28 and boxes 29-32 contain news-clippings collected by John W. Johnston, Mary Johnston, and Elizabeth Johnston; these clippings are about local Virginia news in the late 1800's, the suffrage movement, the peace movement, and Mary Johnston's novels.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Jane Addams with Mary Johnston, 1915; 1917; 1 lettergram; 1 TL (Box Box 1)
  - Viola Allen to Mary Johnston, 1901-1903; 4 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - American Play Company to Mary Johnston, 1916; 7 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Joseph Ames to Mary Johnston, 1911-1913; 1934; 7 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Stringfellow Barr to Mary Johnston, 1932; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Francis L. Berkeley to Elizabeth Johnston, 1946-1947; 1950; 1955; 10 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Alice Stone Blackwell to Mary Johnston, 1910-1914; 4 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Ernest F. Boddington with Mary Johnston, 1900-1902; 13 TLS; 46 ALS; 7 TL (Box Box 1)
  - Ernest F. Boddington with Mary Johnston and Major John W. Johnston, 1903-1904; 8 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Ernest F. Boddington with Mary Johnston's sister and lawyers, 1905; 1 AL; 1 TLS; 2 TL (Box Box 1)
  - Ernest F. Boddington with Mary Johnston, 1915; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Edward Bok to Mary Johnston, 1902-1910; 4 TLS; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - C. L. Bouve to John W. Rumsey, concerning copy rights on Mary Johnston's novel, 1940 Aug 14; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Claude Bragdon to Mary Johnston, 1921; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Carl Brandt with Mary Johnston, 1920; 8 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Zelma Brandt and Carl Brandt with Mary Johnston, 1921-1922; 31M TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Carl Brandt to Mary Johnston, 1923; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Zelma Brandt to Mary Johnston, 1924; 3 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Zelma Brandt and Carl Brandt to Mary Johnston, 1925;1927; 5 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Carl Brandt with Mary Johnston, 1928; 10 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Zelma Brandt and Carl Brandt to and with Mary Johnston, 1929; 9 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Carl Brandt with Mary Johnston, 1931-1932; 39 TLS; 2 TL(copies) (Box Box 1)
  - Zelma Brandt and Carl Brandt to and with Mary Johnston, 1933-1936; 34 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Carl Brandt with Eloise Johnston, 1936-1941; 45 TLS; 8 TL; 2 TL(drafts) (Box Box 1)
  - Van Wyck Brooksto Mary Johnston, 1933; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Taylor Burke to Eloise Johnston, 1937; 2 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Struthers Burt to Mary Johnston, 1934; 1 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Thornton Butterworth to Mary Johnston, 1935; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Richard E. Byrd to Mary Johnston, 1911; 4 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - James Branch Cabell to Mary Johnston, 1916; 1919; 2 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Stuart Chase to Mary Johnston, 1935; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - J. H. Claiborne to Mary Johnston, 1920; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Lucy Coleman to and with Mary Johnston, 1904; 1906; 6 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Confederate Chapters to Mary Johnston, 1899; 1905; 1907; 1910; 10 ALS; 6 TLS (Box Box 1)
  - Jessie Benton Cooke to Mary Johnston, 1921-1922; 2 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Ray Costelloto Mary Johnston, 1910; 6 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Catherine Cushing to and with Eloise Johnston, 1936; 1940; 5 TLS; 6 ALS (Box Box 1)
  - Elliot Dangerfield to Mary Johnston, 1904; 1906; 1911; 3 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Colgate W. Darden, Jr.to Elizabeth Johnston, 1950; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Rebecca Harding Davisto Mary Johnston, 1904-1908; 27 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Margaret Deland to Mary Johnston, 1898; 1919; 1926; 3 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Theodore Dreiser to Mary Johnston, 1910; 2 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - B. M. Dutton with Mary Johnston, 1911; 2 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Ada Dwyer to Mary Johnston, 1906-1907; 2 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Max Eastman to Mary Johnston, 1912; 1 TLS; 1 ALS(frag.) (Box Box 2)
  - Virginia Randolph Ellett to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Equal Suffrage League of Virginiawith Mary Johnston, 1920; 2 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - John Farrington to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Annie Fieldsto Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - John Finley to Mary Johnston, 1900; 5 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Hamilton Fish to Mary Johnston, 1917; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Sir Forbes-Robertson to Mary Johnston, 1912; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Harriet Ford to Mary Johnston, 1902-1908; 1910; 1914; 39 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Harold Freedman to Mary Johnston, 1926; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Zona Gale to Mary Johnston, 1915; 1920; 7 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - R. L. Giffen to Mary Johnston, 1915; 3 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Jeannette L. Gilderwith Mary Johnston, 1899-1900; 8 TLS; 1 TL (Box Box 2)
  - Charlotte Perkins Gilman to Mary Johnston, 1911-1917; 1923; 4 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Ellen Glasgow to Mary Johnston, 1904-1908; 1914; 1935-1936; 21 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Arthur Goodrich to Eloise Johnston, 1936; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Armistead C. Gordon to Mary Johnston, 1920; 1 ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Blanche Grant to Mary Johnston, 1935; 1 TLS (Box Box 2)
  - Ferris Greenslet to and with Mary Johnston, 1909-1917; 165 TLS; 5 ALS; 17 TL (Box Box 2)
  - Ferris Greenslet to and with Mary Johnston, 1921-1922; 1925-1928; 13 TLS; 3 TL; 1 ALS (Box Box 3)
  - Ferris Greensletfrom Mary Johnston, 1929; 2 TL(drafts) (Box Box 3)
  - Ferris Greenslet to Mary Johnston, 1930-1932; 1935-1936; 6 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - Ferris Greenslet with Eloise Johnston, 1936; 6 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - James K. Hackett to Mary Johnston, 1901; 1 TL (Box Box 3)
  - Harper and Brothers to and with Mary Johnston, 1902-1905; 1907; 1910; 45 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - Harper and Brothers to Eloise Johnston, 1936; 1 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - Bertram Harrisonand Carl Brandt with Mary Johnston, 1931; 7 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - Henry Sydnor Harrison to Mary Johnston, 1907; 1909-1910; 1912-1913; 4 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - James A. Harrison to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 3)
  - Archibald Henderson to Mary Johnston, 1921; 1 ALS (Box Box 3)
  - Burton J. Hendrick to Mary Johnston, 1922; 1937; 2 ALS (Box Box 3)
  - Burton J. Hendrick to Eloise Johnston, 1937; 1 ALS (Box Box 3)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Co. to and with Mary Johnston, 1898-1908; 1933; 239 TLS; 36 ALS; 6 TL (Box Box 3)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Co. to Eloise Johnston, 1937; 1 TLS (Box Box 3)
  - Coralie Johnstonfrom Mary Johnston, 1898; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Coralie Johnston to Mary Johnston, 1900-1902; 1905; 1909; 27 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Johnston with Mary Johnston, 1906; 2 TL (Box Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Johnston with Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission, 1956; 1 TLS; 1 TL (Box Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Johnston with Carlie Ely, 1957; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Birthday notes from "Ea" [Eloise Johnston]to "Day" [Mary Johnston], [1920 and 19 Nov 21]; 2 items (Box Box 4)
  - Eloise Johnston with Mary Johnston, 1924; 3 TL (Box Box 4)
  - Major John W. Johnstonfrom Mary Johnston, [1902]; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Major John W. Johnstonletters concerning the Civil War, 1861; 1865; 1903; 3 TL(copies) (Box Box 4)
  - Major John W. Johnston- condolences on death of; addressed to Mary Johnston, 1905; 23 ALS; 2 TLS (Box Box 4)
  - Alice Kauler to Mary Johnston, 1902; 1 TLS (Box Box 4)
  - Basil King to Mary Johnston, 1920-1922; 2 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Bernadine Kisse to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - J. Krishnamurtito Mary Johnston, 1926; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Otto Kyllman to and with Mary Johnston, 1900; 1902-1918; 1920; 28 ALS; 97 TLS; 15 TL (Box Box 4)
  - Fola La Follette to Mary Johnston, 1910; 2 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Liebler and Co.with Mary Johnston, 1914; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Judge Ben B. Lindsay to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Martha Shepard Lippincott to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1902-1903; 1908; 8 ALS (Box Box 4)
  - Little, Brown and Co. to Mary Johnston, 1931; 1933; 2 TLS (Box Box 4)
  - Little, Brown and Co. to Eloise Johnston, 1936; 2 TLS (Box Box 4)
  - George Barr McCutcheon to Mary Johnston, 1909; 1912; 1916; 4 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Marian MacDowell to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Elisabeth Marbury to and with Mary Johnston, 1899; 1900-1901; 1908; 1914; 44 TLS; 11 ALS; 12 TL (Box Box 5)
  - Julia Marlowe to Mary Johnston and Houghton Mifflin and Co., 1900-1901; 2 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Julia Marlowe to and with Mary Johnston, 1907-1909; 2 TLS; 6 ALS; 1 TL; 3 Telegrams (Box Box 5)
  - Julia Marlowe Southern to Mary Johnston, 1915; 2 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Lucy Stone Masonfrom Mary Johnston, 1923-1930; 3 copies made for the "Life" (Box Box 5)
  - Margaret Meredith to Mary Johnston, 1904; 7 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Wyndham Meredithwith Mary Johnston, 1908; 4 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - Nannie J. Minor to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Mary Morgan to Mary Johnston, 1900-1903; 26 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Mary Morganand Nina Morgan to Mary Johnston, 1905-1906; 9 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Nina Morgan to Mary Johnston, 1907; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Senator John T. Morgan to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1902-1905; 1909-1910; 19 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Myrtis Morgan to Eloise Johnston, 1936; 1 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - Mary Munford to and with Mary Johnston, 1917-1919; 3 TLS; 1 TL (Box Box 5)
  - Meredith Nickelson to Mary Johnston, 1910-1911; 2 ALS; 1 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - A. R. Orage to Mary Johnston, 1926-1933; 12 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Jessie Orage to Mary Johnston, 1934; Telegram; Printed Announcement (Box Box 5)
  - Thomas M. Osborne to Mary Johnston, 1915; 1 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - Grant Overton to Mary Johnston, 1922; 2 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - Alice Page to Mary Johnston, 1900; 6 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Arthur Page to Mary Johnston, 1922; 1 TLS (Box Box 5)
  - Thomas Nelson Page to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Walter Hines Page to Mary Johnston, 1899-1900; 1902-1903; 1907; 19 ALS; 4 TLS; 3 TL (Box Box 5)
  - Albert Bigelow Paine to Mary Johnston, 1899-1901; 4 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Bliss Perry to and with Mary Johnston, 1899-1901; 5 ALS; 23 TLS; 1 TL (Box Box 5)
  - A. H. Plecker to Mary Johnston, 1902; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Ernest Poole toand from Mary Johnston, 1918; 1 TLS; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Roger A. Pryor to Mary Johnston, 1909; 1 ALS (Box Box 5)
  - Paul R. Reynoldsto and with Mary Johnston, 1901-1907; 1909; 1914; 1917; 2 ALS; 36 TLS; 4 TL; 1 Telegram (Box Box 6)
  - Richmond Times-DispatchEditor from Mary Johnston, 1917; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - William T. Rigby to Major John W. Johnston, 1902; 1904; 2 ALS; 3 TLS w/enc; 1 TL (Box Box 6)
  - William T. Rigby to Mary Johnston, 1905; 1907; 1909-1910; 5 TLS; 1 ALS; 1 TL (Box Box 6)
  - Kate Douglas Riggsto Mary Johnston, 1905; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Eleanor Robson to Mary Johnston, 1902; 3 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Eleanor Robson to Mary Johnston, [1903]-[1904]; 31 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Eleanor Robson to Mary Johnston, 1905; 4 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Anna Katherine Green Rohlfsto Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - John Rumseywith Mary Johnston, [1914]-1915; 7 TLS; 4 TL; 7 TL(drafts); 1 TL(frag.); 1 Telegram (Box Box 6)
  - John W. Rumseywith Eloise Johnston, 1940-1941; 4 TLS; 3 TL(drafts) (Box Box 6)
  - Ada Dwyer Russell to Mary Johnston, 1903; 1906; 3 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Roger Scaife to Mary Johnston, 1934; 1 TLS (Box Box 6)
  - Horace Scudder to Mary Johnston, 1899; 3 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Ellery Sedgwick to Mary Johnston, 1901; 1909-1910; 1912; 1916; 5 ALS; 4 TLS (Box Box 6)
  - Ellery Sedgwick to Mary Johnston; Eloise Johnston to Ellery Sedgwick, 1936; 2 TLS (Box Box 6)
  - Dr. Anna Howard Shaw to Mary Johnston; Fred R. Kirby to Anna Howard Shaw, 1910; 2 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - The Anna Howard Shaw Annuity Fund- letter to Mary Johnstonrequesting her participation, 1917; 1 TLS (Box Box 6)
  - Edward Shelton to Mary Johnston, [1933]; 2 TLS (Box Box 6)
  - Lizzie K. Sherrard to Mary Johnston, n.y. Sep 8; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - May Sinclair to Mary Johnston, [1904]; 1907; [1912]; 4 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - E. H. Sothern to Mary Johnston, 1912; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Ray [Costello] Strachey to Mary Johnston, 1916; 1 ALS (Box Box 6)
  - Evelyn Thomsomfrom Mary Johnston, 1920-1936; 104 TL(copies) (Box Box 6)
  - Julia Tutwiler to and with Mary Johnston, 1914-1916; 7 TLS; 5 TL (Box Box 7)
  - Alice Tyler to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1912; 11 ALS; 2 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - George Tyler to and with Mary Johnston, 1900-1903; 1905; 23 TLS; 3 AL; TL frag.; 4 Telegrams (Box Box 7)
  - Edward Valentine to Mary Johnston, 1900; 4 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Lila Valentine to and with Mary Johnston, 1903; 1910; 4 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Lila Valentinewith Mary Johnston and Eloise Johnston, 1912-1913; 3 ALS; 1 TL; 2 AL(frag) (Box Box 7)
  - Lila Valentinewith Mary Johnston, 1915-1916; 2 ALS; 1 TL; TL frag. (Box Box 7)
  - Henry Van Dyke to Mary Johnston, 1900; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - University of Richmond Library to Elizabeth Johnston, 1951; 1 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - University of Virginia- Invitation to 100th Anniversary of Founding of University of Virginia, 1920-1921; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Virginia Historical Society to Mary Johnston, 1899; Printed letter, signed (Box Box 7)
  - Edward Wagenknecht to Mary Johnston, 1931-1932; 5 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Edward Wagenknecht to Mary Johnston, 1934-1935; 4 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Edward Wagenknecht with Eloise Johnston, 1937; 1 TLS; 1 TL (Box Box 7)
  - Dugald Stewart Walker to Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Galbraith Welch to and with Mary Johnston, 1915-1916; 9 TLS; 4 TL (Box Box 7)
  - Roberta Wellford to Mary Johnston and Eloise Johnston, 1910; 10 ALS; 1 TLS; 1 APCS (Box Box 7)
  - Roberta Wellford to and with Mary Johnston, 1912;1919; n.d.; 3 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Roberta Wellford, miscellaneous letters, 1936; 3 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Stanley Weyman to Mary Johnston, 1911; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Walter White to Mary Johnston; Albert Spingarn to Mary Johnston, 1923; 1 TLS; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Walter White to Mary Johnston, 1935 Dec; 1936 Jan; 2 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Ellen Whitney to Mary Johnston, 1900-1908; 1916; 44 ALS; 1 ALS frag; 7 AL frag. (Box Box 7)
  - Kate Douglas Wiggin to Mary Johnston, 1901; 1908; 3 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Louise Collier Wilcoxto Mary Johnston, 1910; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - College of William and Mary to Mary Johnston, 1919; 1 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - James Southall Wilson to Mary Johnston, 1931; 2 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Mary E. Woolley to Mary Johnston, 1915; 2 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - N. C. Wyeth to Mary Johnston, 1910-1912; 12 ALS; 1 ALS frag; 1 Telegram (Box Box 7)
  - Elinor Wylie to Mary Johnston, 1926; 1 ALS (Box Box 7)
  - Yale University Pressto Mary Johnston, 1918-1919; 3 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Stark Young to Mary Johnston, 1936; 2 TLS (Box Box 7)
  - Women's Suffrage, miscellaneous correspondence to and from Mary Johnston, 1910-1913; 1915-1917; ca. 159 items (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence re the Bell and Johnston families, 1827; 1862; 1864; 1891; 1902; 1935; 6 items (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence with Mary Johnstonre: Peace movement, 1916-1919; 5 TL (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence from editors to Mary Johnston, 1899; 28 items (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence requesting right to dramatize To Have And To Hold, 1900; 4 TLS; 1 ALS (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous invitations for social affairs or for membership in organization, 1910-1917; ca. 20 items (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Mary Johnstonabout War stories, 1912-1919; 12 items (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Eloise Johnston and Elizabeth Johnston, 1951; 1955; 1959; 2 items (Box Box 8)
  - Correspondence from miscellaneous publishers to Elizabeth Johnston, 1953; 4 ALS (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence concerning a Musical version and program for To Have and To Hold, 1955; 1 TLS; 2 TL(copies) (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Mary Johnston, 1898-1900; 122 items (Box Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Mary Johnston, 1900-1906; ca. 433 items (Box Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence with Mary Johnston, 1907-1923; 1927; 1929-1932;1934-1936; ca. 325 items (Box Box 10)
- Manuscripts
  - List of Short Stories- published and unpublished, AMs and TMs (Box Box 11)
  - The Abbe, 1909; AMs and TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "Added Space"- published short story, n.d.; 2 TMs and TMs frag. (Box Box 11)
  - "The Angel"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "The Attic Room"- published short story, [1935]; 2 TMs (Box Box 11)
  - Audrey- newspaper clippings about the novel, 1900-1902; 75 clippings (Box Box 11)
  - Audrey- newspaper clippings re dramatization of Mary Johnston's novel, 1902-1903; 202 clippings (Box Box 11)
  - Audrey- fragment of book, [1904]; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "The Baptizing"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "Black Lace"- published short story, 1928; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "The Blue Dress"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "Broomsedge House"- unpublished short story, n.d.; 2 TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "The Buccaneer"- published short story, 1928; 2 TMs (Box Box 11)
  - "Buried Silver"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 11)
  - The Case of Fanny Nethaway- chapters 2, 3, unpublished and unfinished, TMs(carbon) (Box Box 12)
  - "The Choice"- unpublished short story, [1922]; TMs(carbon) (Box Box 12)
  - "The Church Festival"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - "Courtship of Pocahontas", [1931]; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - "The Dark Princess"(or "Powhatan's Laughter") - unfinished, [1931]; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - Drury Randall, 1934; Galley Proofs w/autograph corrections (Box Box 12)
  - The Elephant, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - "Elephants Through the Country"- published short story, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - "The End of the World"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 12)
  - The Far Country- unpublished, unfinished novel, chapters 1-20, 1935; TMs w/autograph corrections, autograph notes (Box Box 12)
  - The Far Country- unpublished, unfinished novel, chapters 21- 30, notes, 1935; TMs w/autograph corrections, autograph notes (Box Box 13)
  - The Far Country- unpublished unfinished novel, chapters 1- 25 - duplicate copy, 1935; TMs(carbon) (Box Box 13)
  - "Gettysburg"- published article, 1912; AN (Box Box 13)
  - Reprint from "The Long Roll", 1912; Printed matter (Box Box 13)
  - "The God from the Machine"- unpublished short story, n.d.; 2 TMs (Box Box 13)
  - "Great Aunt Aurelia"- published short story, [1928]; TMs(carbon) (Box Box 13)
  - "Hagar"- Author's note for chapter 10, [1912]; TMs frag. (Box Box 13)
  - "If a Weasel Crosses Your Path"- published short story, 1932; TMs(carbon) (Box Box 13)
  - "Jack O'Lantern"- unpublished short story, n.d.; 2 TMs(carbon) (Box Box 13)
  - "The Laboratory"- a poem, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 13)
  - Lewis Rand- published novel, chapters 1-5, 1907; AMs (Box Box 13)
  - Lewis Rand- published novel, chapters 6-8; 10-19; 22, 1907; AMs (Box Box 14)
  - Early drafts of Lewis Rand, TMs (Box Box 14)
  - Early drafts of Lewis Rand, AMs (Box Box 14)
  - Notes for Lewis Rand, TMs (Box Box 15)
  - Notes for Lewis Rand, AMs and notebook (Box Box 15)
  - The Long Roll- author's note, [1908]; AMs, TMs and notebook (Box Box 15)
  - The Long Roll- illustrations pertaining to, 1910; 2 items (Box Box 15)
  - The Long Roll, 1911; TMs frag. (Box Box 15)
  - "The Lost Doll"- unpublished short story, n.d.; 2 TMs (Box Box 15)
  - "The Mockingbird"- published short story, 1928; TMs (Box Box 15)
  - "Nemesis"- published in The Century Magazine, 1923; Printed material (Box Box 15)
  - "One Night"- published short story, 1920 Jul 25; 2 TMs (Box Box 15)
  - "Ponce de Leon"- unpublished blank verse narrative, n.d.; 2 TMs (Box Box 15)
  - "The Prodigal Son"- unpublished short story, 1933; TMs (Box Box 15)
  - Quest- unpublished unfinished novel, [1934]; TMs (Box Box 15)
  - Quest- unpublished, unfinished novel, [1934]; TMs (Box Box 16)
  - "The River James"- published poem, 1923; TMs and The Reviewer (Box Box 16)
  - Roger Sarre and Dona Maria- unpublished, unfinished novel, chapters 1-17, TMs (Box Box 16)
  - "The Ships Sailed Up the Stream", [1931]; TMs (Box Box 16)
  - Sir Mortimer- published novel, 1903; Author's Proof (Box Box 16)